Guide to the James R. Mellow Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James R. Mellow papers
1940-1999
YCAL MSS 297
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
40.87
(53 boxes)
The collection consists of research material, writings, correspondence, audiocassettes, printed material, personal papers, financial papers, photographs, and other papers, documenting the work of James R. Mellow as an art critic, a book reviewer, and a literary biographer, shedding particular light on his biographies of Gertrude Stein, Nathaniel Hawthorne, F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, Ernest Hemingway, and Walker Evans.
Mellow, James Robert, 1926-1997
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Augie Capaccio, 1999-2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 34-35 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
James R. Mellow (1926-1997)
James R. Mellow was born in Gloucester, Massachusetts in 1926, and attended Northwestern University. Beginning in 1950, he wrote about art and literature for Commonweal, ARTnews, and Arts Magazine, eventually becoming editor of the latter. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, he was an art critic for The New York Times. Mellow's books of literary biography include: Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company (1974), Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times (1980), Invented Lives: F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald (1984) and Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences (1992). He also wrote a biography of the photographer Walker Evans, which was published posthumously in 1999.
Mellow died at his home in Rockport, Massachusetts in 1997.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of research material, writings, correspondence, audiocassettes, printed material, personal papers, financial papers, photographs, and other papers, documenting the work of James R. Mellow as an art critic, a book reviewer, and a literary biographer, shedding particular light on his biographies of Gertrude Stein, Nathaniel Hawthorne, F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, Ernest Hemingway, and Walker Evans.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: I. April 1999 Acquisition. II. November 2003 Acquisition. III. October 2007 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, correspondence and writings can be found in all three groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Art criticism -- United States; Art critics -- United States -- Archives; Authors, American -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Biographers -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Art critics -- United States; Biographers -- United States; Evans, Walker, 1903-1975; Fitzgerald, F. Scott (Francis Scott), 1896-1940; Fitzgerald, Zelda, 1900-1948; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Mellow, James Robert, 1926-1997; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946
- April 1999 Acquisition, 1950-1996; 1; 14.29; (17 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into four series: Research and Writing Files; Other Writings; Correspondence; and Other Papers.
  General note
  Formerly classed as Uncat ZA MS 623.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Similar material can be found in November 2003 Acquisition and October 2007 Acquisition.
  - Research and Writing Files
    Arranged by title of work.
    - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company
      - Typescript, early draft and photocopy, undated; 2 (Box 1)
      - Typescript, 1972; 15 (Box 1)
      - Typescript, next to last revisions first half, undated; 2 (Box 1)
      - Proofs, 1973; 2 (Box 1)
      - Stein & Music lecture, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Stein: sheet music Capitals Capitals by Gertrude Stein and Virgil Thomson, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
      - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein and Company, [1972]; 6 (Box 2)
      - New York Times article on Gertrude Stein, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Yale notes, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Notes from books read, undated (Box 2)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences
      - Typescript, undated; 8 (Box 2)
      - Chaps., 1987-89; 5 (Box 3)
      - Typescript, 1988-89; 9 (Box 3)
      - Hemingway's Passport: photocopy, undated (Box 3)
      - Ernest and Mary Hemingway's will, photocopy, 1992 (Box 3)
      - Lectures relating to Hemingway, undated (Box 3)
      - Page proofs
    - Invented Lives: F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald
      - Part 4: typescript, undated; 3 (Box 4)
      - Scenario: typescript, undated; 2 (Box 4)
      - Printed copy (2 copies), undated; 6 (Box 4)
      - Typescript, undated; 4 (Box 4)
      - "A" typescript, undated; 4 (Box 4)
      - Notebook, 1982 (Box 4)
      - First draft notes, undated; 2 (Box 5)
      - Printed version, photocopies, undated (Box 5)
      - Loose Ends I: typescript, undated (Box 5)
      - IV Weekends at Ellerslie: typescript, undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous pages, typescript and photocopy, 1983; undated; 3 (Box 5)
      - Part I Reading Draft, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
      - Part II: typescript, 1981 (Box 5)
      - Part II: preliminary reading draft, 1982 (Box 5)
      - Part III: typescript, undated (Box 5)
      - Checklist of permissions, undated (Box 5)
      - Typescript, partial, undated (Box 5)
      - Photocopied material, undated (Box 5)
      - Typescript, undated; 5 (Box 5)
      - Fitzgerald manuscript checked against proofs, 1984 June (Box 5)
      - Notes on Fitzgerald, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Notes, 1984 (Box 5)
      - Research materials, photocopy, undated (Box 5)
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times
      - Early draft Quotations checked at Essex Institute, undated; 2 (Box 6)
      - Final typescript through Book III, undated; 3 (Box 6)
      - The Hawthornes, undated; 6 (Box 6)
      - Book II, undated (Box 6)
      - Manuscript: photocopy, undated (Box 6)
      - Chapter 16, undated (Box 6)
      - Master copy before typing, undated; 2 (Box 7)
      - Jon's corrections. Book III. Used to check original letters, etc., undated; 2 (Box 7)
      - Book IV: copy used for checking original letters. Includes Jonathan's corrections before final typescript, undated; 2 (Box 7)
      - Draft I, undated; 5 (Box 7)
      - Master copy before typing, 1979 April 6; 2 (Box 7)
      - Jon's corrections on 1958 copy, undated; 2 (Box 7)
      - Book IV. Sue's copy, undated; 2 (Box 7)
      - Corrected typescript, 1980 January 7; 2 (Box 8)
      - Early version of notes with annotations, undated (Box 8)
      - Berg queries, undated (Box 8)
      - Typescript-first, undated; 5 (Box 8)
      - Book IV. Copy to typist, undated; 4 (Box 8)
      - Book II: typescript, undated; 3 (Box 8)
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 8)
      - Book IV: copy edited, undated; 3 (Box 8)
      - Extra set of notes. Missing pages sent to Jon to look over, undated (Box 8)
      - Nathaniel Hawthorne Citizen of Somewhere Else: manuscript, undated (Box 8)
      - Page proofs
      - Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times: Notes and Writings, undated; 3 (Box 9)
      - Author's Notes, undated (Box 9)
      - Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times: proofs, 1980; 2 (Box 9)
      - Hawthorne's Lost Notebook 1835-41, undated (Box 9)
      - Research on the Smalls, undated (Box 9)
      - Una Hawthorne Letters 1861-70, undated (Box 9)
      - The Sophistry of Passion, undated (Box 9)
      - Essex 1 Transcripts, undated (Box 9)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 9)
      - Still Pictures In The Audiovisual Archives Division of The National Archives: by Mayfield S. Bray, undated (Box 9)
      - List of Illustrations, undated (Box 9)
      - Photocopied Pictures, undated (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous Type Copies, undated (Box 9)
      - Queries to send, undated (Box 9)
      - Notes & Queries Manuscript, undated (Box 9)
      - Revised literary sections, undated (Box 9)
      - Massachusetts Historical Society, undated (Box 9)
      - Iowa State Historical Society, undated (Box 9)
      - Essex Institute Material Checked, undated (Box 9)
      - Huntington Library Photocopies, undated (Box 9)
      - Bowdoin College Photocopies, undated (Box 9)
      - Bancroft Library Photocopies, undated (Box 9)
      - Bancroft Library Photocopy of Hawthorne's Diary; 1858, undated (Box 9)
      - Beinecke Corrections, undated (Box 9)
      - Hawthorne Beinecke Transcripts, undated (Box 9)
      - Queries, undated (Box 9)
      - New Hampshire Historical Society Pierce Papers, undated (Box 9)
      - Pearson Transcripts 1850, undated (Box 10)
      - Pearson Transcripts 1813-1849, undated (Box 10)
      - Hawthorne Lecture Notes, undated (Box 10)
      - Photocopies Queries Misc., undated (Box 10)
      - Hawthorne Notes, undated; 2 (Box 10)
      - Boston Public Library, undated (Box 10)
      - Hawthorne Corrections, undated (Box 10)
      - Hawthorne Reviews, undated; 2 (Box 10)
      - Notes, undated (Box 10)
  - Other writings
    - [Brook Farm]
      - Manuscript [One folder also contains manuscript of book reviews and articles.], undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - Crystal Palaces, Geodesic Domes. A Century of Modern Design
      - Crystal Palaces: Introduction correspondence, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Chapter I: The Great Exhibition of 1851, [1969] (Box 10)
    - Young Curators: Careers on Hold
      - Training of Curators; notes, undated (Box 10)
      - Times Article, undated (Box 10)
      - Aviso, undated; 2 (Box 10)
      - The Curatorial Catch 22 by Mellow, undated (Box 10)
      - Resumes, undated; 6 (Box 10)
      - Museum News: magazine, 1986 (Box 10)
      - Times Curator File, 1986 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 10)
      - Clippings (Box 10)
      - Articles, 1978-1988; 2 (Box 11)
      - DLB (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Miscellaneous and unsorted correspondence is arranged at the end.
    - "A" General (Box 12)
    - Ambler, Louise (Box 12)
    - American Counsil of Learned Societies (Box 12)
    - Angela, Mother M. (Box 12)
    - Avon (Box 12)
    - "B" General (Box 12)
    - Blue Cross/Blue Shield (Box 12)
    - Bodleian Library (Box 12)
    - Book Promotion (Box 12)
    - Borchardt, Watson, 1979-1985; 4 (Box 12)
    - The Boston Athenaeum (Box 12)
    - Bowdoin College (Box 12)
    - The Browning Institute (Box 12)
    - Business correspondence (Box 12)
    - "C" General (Box 12)
    - The Cleveland Museum of Art (Box 12)
    - Concord Free Public Library (Box 12)
    - "D" General (Box 12)
    - Design Book (Box 12)
    - "E" General (Box 12)
    - Essex Institute (Box 12)
    - "F" General (Box 12)
    - Fogg Art Musuem (Box 12)
    - "G" General (Box 12)
    - Gallup (Box 12)
    - Galassi (Box 12)
    - GSA (Box 12)
    - Gechtoff: Gruenebaum (Box 12)
    - Gollin, Rita (Box 12)
    - "H" General (Box 12)
    - Houghton Library (Box 12)
    - Houghton Mifflin, 3 (Box 12)
    - House of the Seven Gables (Box 12)
    - Humanities Research Center (Box 12)
    - "I" General (Box 12)
    - Idol, John (Box 12)
    - Industrial design reviews (Box 12)
    - "J" General (Box 12)
    - Journalism (Box 12)
    - "K" General (Box 12)
    - Kramer (Box 12)
    - "L-M" General, 2 (Box 12)
    - Massachusetts Historical Society (Box 12)
    - Mencken, Harold, permission lists, photo (Box 12)
    - "N" General (Box 12)
    - National Archives and Records Service (Box 12)
    - National Portrait Gallery (Box 12)
    - New Hampshire Historical Society (Box 12)
    - New York Public Library (Box 12)
    - "O" General (Box 12)
    - Ober/Schreiber permission requests, 2 (Box 12)
    - "P" General (Box 12)
    - Praeger: John Hoffman (Box 12)
    - Proposals (Box 12)
    - "Q-R" General, 2 (Box 12)
    - Reviews, articles: correspondence, 3 (Box 13)
    - "S" General (Box 13)
    - Shaker Community, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Smith, Neal (Box 13)
    - Re: Stein (Box 13)
    - "T-Z" General, 4 (Box 13)
    - University of California (Box 13)
    - Yale Center for British Art (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Early Correspondence, 1950-1970; 3 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1975; 5 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1986; 8 (Box 14)
  - Other Papers
    Arranged alphabetically by file title.
    - Adventures In Reading And Writing, undated (Box 15)
    - Albert Eugene Gallatin and His Circle; catalog, 1986 (Box 15)
    - American Book Awards, 1983 (Box 15)
    - The Book of Summer, undated (Box 15)
    - The Commonweal, 1960-65 (Box 15)
    - The Dial Collection, undated (Box 15)
    - Daily Planner, 1986 (Box 15)
    - Equitable Center, 1986 (Box 15)
    - Gourmet, the Magazine, 1980 (Box 15)
    - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1984; 2 (Box 15)
    - Margaret Fuller, undated (Box 15)
    - Mellow, James R., Jr.: diploma, 1950 (Box 15)
    - Mellow, James R., Jr.: resume, undated (Box 15)
    - The Metropolitan Museum of Art: report, 1982-83 (Box 15)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, undated (Box 15)
    - New York Times clippings on Vienna, 1986 (Box 15)
    - New York Times clippings, [1968-1986]; 9 (Box 15)
    - New York Times clippings, [1968-1986] (Box 16)
    - New York University Magazine, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Notable Acquisitions, 1984-1985 (Box 16)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 16)
    - Orbituaries A-Z, 5 (Box 16)
    - People Magazine, 1996 (Box 16)
    - Picasso, undated (Box 16)
    - Print Review; magazine photocopied, undated (Box 16)
    - Reminiscences, undated (Box 16)
    - Seminar Material (Box 16)
    - Steinberg, undated (Box 16)
    - Vineyard Books (Box 16)
  - Oversize
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, page proofs (from Research and Writing Files) (Box 17)
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times, page proofs (from Research and Writing Files), 1980; 2 (Box 17)
- November 2003 Acquisition, circa 1984-1996; 2; 16.21; (20 boxes)
  Organized at the box level into three series: Research and Writing Files, Other Papers, and Audiocassettes.
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 615.
  Similar material can be found in April 1999 Acquisition and October 2007 Acquisition.
  - Research and Writing Files
    - Walker Evans, 19 (Box 18)
    - Walker Evans, 20 (Box 19)
    - Walker Evans, 23 (Box 20)
    - Walker Evans, 41 (Box 21)
    - Walker Evans, 39 (Box 22)
    - Walker Evans, 49 (Box 23)
    - Walker Evans, 19 (Box 24)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, 9 (Box 24)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, 29 (Box 25)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, 32 (Box 26)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, 14 (Box 27)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, 31 (Box 28)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences, 18 (Box 29)
    - Invented Lives: F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, 18 (Box 29)
    - Invented Lives: F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, 18 (Box 30)
    - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company, 3 (Box 30)
    - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company, 25 (Box 31)
    - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company, 3 (Box 32)
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times, 6 (Box 32)
  - Other Papers
    - Other papers (Box 32)
    - Photographs (Box 33)
  - Audiocassettes
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Dr. G. Robert Saunders, 1992 May 16; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249764)
    - Dub #10, Part I and II; Walker Evans, Methuselah, 1967 August 14; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249772)
    - #10 continued, Part #3; Walker Evans, Methuselah, 1967 August 14; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249780)
    - Tad Brewer, [?]SRM, 1994 May 26; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249798)
    - Dub #12, Part 3, unidentified woman, Bell[?], circa 1970; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249806)
    - Leslei + Jane in Rockport ?, undated; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249814)
    - Walker Evans and Jerry Thompson, Old Lyme / WE and JT, Charles [?], 1973 April 7; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249822)
    - Walker Evans / Bill Stott, 1971 April 19; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249830)
    - Soundtrack Sedal Paka[?] Film, 1968; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249848)
    - Jerry Thompson / Marcia Due, 1992 August 27; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249855)
    - Jane Sargeant / JRM, 1994 May 25; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249863)
    - Jane Sargeant, 1993 May 13; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249871)
    - H. Kramer / JRM, 1994 April 23; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249889)
    - Jane Sargeant, 1993 May 12; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249897)
    - A.T.J. Hills: Doro[?], Jerry Thompson / Marcia Due, undated; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249921)
    - Alice Morris / Colby Welles, JRM, 1993 September 3; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249939)
    - Walker Evans /JT, Evans at Williams and in Paris, 1973 February 1; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002091249947)
    - Walker Evans: Jane Sargeant, 1991 June 15; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002091249954)
    - Thompson / Evans / LTL, 1973 February 4; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002091249962)
    - Alston Purvis / JM, 1993 July 17; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002091249970)
    - #3 interview, Walker Evans / Bill Stott, 1971 April 19; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002091249988)
    - Evans + Katz / Jerry Thompson cont., Eak[?] Press, 1973 February 4; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002091249996)
    - Unidentified, undated; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002091250002)
      Scope and Contents
      Content includes a variety of Broadway musical selections.
    - Jane Sargeant / JRM, Salisbury, CT, 1995 May 19; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360019)
    - Katz / M[?], 1992 August 11-12; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360027)
    - Jane Sargeant, second tape, 1993 May 12; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360035)
    - Walker Evans / Mary Knollenberg, 1991 June 14; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360043)
    - Walker Evans, Yale Lecture, Lyric Documentary, Post Cah[?], undated; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360050)
    - John + Dorothy Hill, 1992 September 12-13; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360068)
    - Isabelle Story / JRM, 1994 June 8; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360076)
    - Walker Evans / unidentifed woman, #12, undated; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360084)
    - Walker Evans: John Hill, 1991 June 10; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360092)
    - Marcia Due + Jerry Thompson, 1992 August 27; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360100)
    - Katz / Mary Hall, 1992 August 11-12; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002099360118)
  - Oversize
    - Walker Evans (from Research and Writing Files), 2 (Box 36)
    - Walker Evans (from Research and Writing Files), 2 (Box 37)
- October 2007 Acquisition, 1940s-1999; 3; 10.37; (16 boxes)
  Organized into six series: Correspondence; Research and Writing Files; Other Writings; Personal Papers; Printed Material; and Objects.
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 978.
  Similar material can be found in April 1999 Acquisition and November 2003 Acquisition.
  - Correspondence, circa 1970s-1994
    Also found are other papers which relate to Mellow's professional and personal life.
    - Helen Stein Clippings, circa 1970s-1986 (Box 38)
    - Praeger, Holt Rinehart, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 38)
    - Stein Copyright, 1973-1992 (Box 38)
    - General, 1976-1988 (Box 38)
    - "Jellsneck-Dodge Etc. - Dr. Kramer", 1981-1982 (Box 38)
    - Houghton Mifflin Royalty Statements, 1981-1990 (Box 38)
    - General, 1986-1987 (Box 38)
    - Borchardt, 1987-1988 (Box 38)
    - General, 1987-1989 (Box 38)
    - Kennedy Library, 1988-1992 (Box 38)
    - Charmed Circle, circa 1989-1990 (Box 38)
    - General, 1989-1991 (Box 38)
    - Gloucester Material, 1990 (Box 38)
    - Borchardt Contracts, circa 1990 (Box 38)
    - Notes Prior to Spacing, circa 1990 (Box 38)
    - Conference Notes - 12/1/89, circa 1990 (Box 38)
    - Bibliography, circa 1990 (Box 38)
    - Item Paperback Reviews, Etc., 1990-1993 (Box 38)
    - General, 1991; 2 (Box 38)
    - General, 1992 (Box 38)
    - Borchardt, 1992 (Box 38)
    - Festival of Authors, 1992 (Box 38)
    - Borchardt, 1993 (Box 38)
    - General, 1993; 2 (Box 38)
    - "Echocardiogram 7/94", 1994 (Box 38)
  - Research and Writing Files, circa 1965-1999
    - Walker Evans
      - Basic Books Marketing Pamphlet (Box 38)
      - Walker Evans Research Material, circa 1994 (Box 38)
      - American Pictures by Peter Sekaer, 1999 (Box 38)
      - Walker Evans Research Material, 3 (Box 38)
      - Notebooks, circa 1993 (Box 39)
      - "Walker Evans Misc", circa 1972 (Box 39)
      - Walker Evans Research Material, 2 (Box 39)
      - Carleton Beals photocopies (Box 39)
      - Art in America (Box 39)
      - Azalai (Box 39)
      - Correspondence regarding Walker Evans, 1994 (Box 39)
      - "1934 - Politics of Vernacular. WE Chapt XI" (Box 39)
      - Photocopies (Box 39)
      - "South New Orleans Etc. - Feb/Mar 1935" (Box 39)
      - "South / Spring 1935", 5 (Box 39)
      - "Negatives Etc. - Not Filed" (photocopies) (Box 39)
      - W.E. Early German Russian Exhibition (Box 39)
      - "Jane's / JRM: lists" (Box 39)
      - Negative Sleeves by Year (Box 39)
      - "Neg. Sleeves Info. 1940+ - 441 East 92nd St." (photocopies) (Box 39)
      - W.E. Subway (Box 39)
      - Important Info. Sleeves (Box 39)
      - Subway Portraits (photocopies) (Box 39)
      - "W.E. Voyages 1932-33 Tahiti, VIII" (Box 39)
      - Contact Prints (photocopies) (Box 39)
      - W.E. Photos Duskjackets (Box 39)
      - 1930-1931 Negative Sleeve #5 (photocopies) (Box 39)
      - Selected Negative Sleeves (photocopies) (Box 39)
      - "W.E. Chapter XXIII" (Box 39)
      - "Bridgeport 1941, Etc. Summer 1941" (Box 40)
      - "Chapter XXII" (Box 40)
      - "W.E. South Photos 1935-36" (Box 40)
      - Loose Material, 4 (Box 40)
    - Invented Lives: F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald
      - Odell correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 40)
      - Rosalind Fuller manuscript, 3 (Box 40)
      - Loose Material (Box 40)
      - Fitzgerald Notes (Box 40)
      - Rosalind Fuller manuscript, 2 (Box 40)
      - Loose Material (Box 40)
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne in His Times
      - The Shock of Recognition (Box 40)
      - Correspondence regarding Hawthorne, circa 1980-1990; 3 (Box 40)
      - NEA - Hawthrone / Melville (Box 40)
      - New England Quarterlies Review - Hawthorne (Box 40)
      - Correspondence: Gordon Hyatt (Box 40)
      - Screenplay - "The Privileged Spot" (Box 40)
      - Newsweek, Oct 6, 1990 (Box 40)
      - Hawthorne Notebook (Box 41)
      - Permissions Requests, 1980 (Box 41)
      - Loose Material, 3 (Box 41)
    - Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences
      - Typescript, corrected, circa 1992; 10 (Box 42)
      - Author's marked set, circa 1992
      - Master proof, circa 1992
    - Hemingway / Hawthorne Material
      Included is scattered material relating to Merrill's research on Nathanial Hawthorne and Ernest Hemingway.
      - Sallie V. Small Widows Pension, 1907 (Box 42)
      - James M. Small Pension Declaration, 1892 (Box 42)
      - Industrial Design, circa 1965 (Box 42)
      - Hawthorne Permissions - John Hopkins U. Correspondence, 1997 (Box 42)
      - Hemingway Photographs (Box 42)
      - Stanford University Libraries Annual Report, 1984-1985 (Box 42)
      - Hemingway / Fitzgerald International Conference, 1993-1994 (Box 42)
      - Boston Globe: Guggenheim-Hemingway, 1986 (Box 42)
      - "Freelance 1989 - Hemingway Misc" (Box 42)
    - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company